Department of English Records UA074
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Department of English Records
1994 -- 2016
1906 -- 2016
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Department of English
School of Arts and Sciences
UA074
1.7 Linear Feet 2 boxes and 1 oversize folder
12 Digital Object(s)
35 Gigabytes
This collection contains the records of the English Department.
Conditions Governing Access
University records are closed for 20 years from the date of their creation. Records older than 20 years that do not pertain to student education, staff and faculty employment and Board of Trustees records are open for research. This collection may require review before it is available for use. Please contact DCA for further details.
Arrangement
This collection is organized in three series: Photographs; Unprocessed accessions; and Events. Files within series are arranged chronologically.
Biographical / Historical
The Department of English was established in 1893. In 1894, it was one of the original departments to offer an undergraduate major to students. The Department of English emerged from the Department of Rhetoric, Logic, and English Literature, which was its predecessor.
The Catalogue of Tufts College for the 1894-1895 academic year describes the Department as follows, "The course of instruction in English aims at both theoretical knowledge and practical results. It begins with extemporaneous composition in the Freshman year. In this exercise, which is weekly, formal theme-writing is avoided. Topics are assigned, with some variety of method, at the time of writing, usually not the same topic for all, but a list is furnished from which each writer may select, giving preference to what is nearest at hand and best understood. The brief essays are subject to criticism both in class and with the individual writers. With suitable modification, this extemporaneous writing is continued at intervals to the end of the course. The formal study of Rhetoric begins with the second year."
Initially, Professor Shipman was the primary instructor in the Department. Professor William Rollin Shipman was born in Granville, Vermont on May 4, 1836. He graduated from Middlebury College in 1859 and subsequently came to head the Green Mountain Institute at South Woodstock, Vermont which he restored to prosperity during his tenure. Professor Shipman later accepted the chair of the Department of Rhetoric, Logic, and English Literature at Tufts. In addition to his administrative duties, Professor Shipman maintained a substantial teaching schedule in the Department. When the Department of Rhetoric, Logic, and English Literature became the Department of English in 1893, Professor Shipman remained the chair of the newly formed department.
Professor David Lee Maulsby served as the Principal of Goddard Seminary, Barre, Vermont before he accepted the chair of English Literature and Oratory at Tufts in 1891. From 1892 to 1895, Professor Maulsby was also the custodian of the Faculty records, first as Clerk and later as Secretary. In 1895, Professor Maulsby joined Professor Shipman in sharing the primary teaching duties in the Department of English.
Professor Maulsby was instrumental in directing and staging the student production of "Ralph Roister Doister" in June, 1895. The production proved to be a great success and even attracted audiences from outside the Tufts community.
Currently, the Department of English ranks among the many prominent departments at Tufts. It offers a highly regarded Ph.D. program whose graduates routinely accept tenure-track faculty positions at colleges and universities throughout the United States.
Scope and Contents
These records include photographs, course descriptions, departmental correspondence and memos, faculty and student directories, and material related to events sponsored by the department.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred by the Department of English, 2002-2017.
Tufts University. Department of English.; Department of English; Curriculum and Instruction -- Academic Departments and Programs; Curriculum and Instruction -- Teaching Material
- Photographs, 1906; UA074.001; 0.0 Linear Feet; 2 Digital Object(s)
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains photographs from productions put on by the English Department.
  Arrangement
  This series is not arranged.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Open for research.
  - "Old Fortunatus", 1906; UA074.001.001.00001 (Box Small Map Case 1 Drawer 4)
    These three photographs are from the 1906 production of the "Old Fortunatus", directed by English professor Thomas Whittemore, and performed for the Semi-Centennial of Tufts College. Prior to 1910 no campus theater group had remained in existence for more than a year. For this production members of the college participated as players as well as individuals from the surrounding area.
    - Fortune, Virtue, Vice and attendents in the Old Fortunatus production, 1906; UA074.001.001.00001.00001 (Box Small Map Case 1 Drawer 4)
      Students; Theater; Theater, Open-air; Plays; Student activities; photographic print; Dekker, Thomas, ca. 1572-1632; Whittemore, Thomas
    - Court scene from the Old Fortunatus production, 1906; UA074.001.001.00001.00002 (Box Small Map Case 1 Drawer 4)
- Additional accessions, 1968 -- 2004; UA074.002
  - Department of English, memos and correspondence and course descriptions, 1968 -- 2004; UA074-002 (Box data_value_missing_0e0cfd6df2a9f0b67c6c749715c6bcdd, Box 1)
    20 years from date of creation.
  - Department of English, memos and correspondence, course descriptions, and address lists, 1992 -- 2002; UA074-001 (Box data_value_missing_d931faf4c04d6c90a5fc5df79560b645, Box 2)
- Events, 2016-11-17 -- 2016-11-18; UA074.003; 10 Digital Object(s); 35 Gigabytes
  This series is arranged chronologically.
  This series is open for research.
  This series contains material related to events sponsored by the English Department.
  - Reflections on the Election of Trump, 2016-11-17; UA074.003.00001; Badiou, Alain; 1 Digital Object(s) 1 digital object containing 4 files.; 13.07 Gigabytes
    One week after Donald Trump's election as president of the United States, Alain Badiou discusses the implications of this unexpected and, for many people, frightening result. He places it in the context of world politics since the 1980s, explaining Trump as a symptom of the failure to imagine a real alternative to global capitalism.
  - 'Modern' Art and 'Contemporary' Art: A False Distinction?, 2016-11-18; UA074.003.00005; Badiou, Alain; 1 Digital Object(s) 1 digital object containing 3 files.; 10.09 Gigabytes
    Alain Badiou argues that the distinction between modern art and contemporary art should be replaced by one between modern art and a new classicism. His lecture focuses on Picasso's painting "Guernica" and César Vallejo's poem "Spain, Take This Cup from Me."
  - Toward a Revival of Pan-Africanism, 2016-11-18; UA074.003.00008; Winter, Cécile; 1 Digital Object(s) 1 digital object containing 3 files; 11.83 Gigabytes
    Cécile Winter discusses French neo-colonialism in Africa and strategies for resisting it. She draws on the philosophy of Alain Badiou and makes connections to the Chinese cultural revolution.